Frederick W. Chesson Connecticut Iron Industry Collection
© 2010 University of Connecticut
Frederick W. Chesson Connecticut Iron Industry Collection.
undated, 1920-1949.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Chesson, Frederick W.
1.0 linear foot.
Resident of Waterbury, Connecticut, and historian of Connecticut business and industry. Collection includes collected literature about the early iron industry in the United States, particularly Massachusetts, Connecticut, New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania.
MSS19990114
Biography
Frederick W. Chesson is a resident of Waterbury, Connecticut, a collector of documents about Connecticut's business and industrial history, and the author of three books about the Connecticut cities of New Haven, Waterbury and Woodbury.
Published Works:
New Haven: from the collection of Charles Rufus Harte, Dover, N.H.: Arcadia, 1995.
Waterbury, Dover, N.H.: Arcadia, 1996.
Around Woodbury, Charleston, S.C.: Arcadia, 2000.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of notes, writings, correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings created or gathered by Charles Rufus Harte and Herbert Cary Keith, presumably in preparation for their writing of the book The Early Iron Industry in Connecticut, written in 1935. While the main focus of the materials in the collection are on the early iron industry in Connecticut, there is also information about the iron industry in Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, and Pennsylvania, particularly the Hopewell Furnace.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Harte, Charles Rufus; Keith, Herbert Cary; Murdock, William Bartlett
Places:
Hopewell Furnace National Historic Site (Pa.); Oxford Furnace (Oxford, N.J.)
Subjects:
Iron industry and trade -- Connecticut.; Iron industry and trade -- New York.; Iron industry and trade -- New Jersey.; Iron industry and trade -- Massachusetts.; Iron industry and trade -- Pennsylvania.; Blast furnaces.; Saugus Iron Works.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Maps.; Manuscripts.; Typescripts.; Notes.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Mr. Frederick W. Chesson in 1999.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Collection, undated, 1920-1949
  - General notes about the early iron industry in the United States, undated, 1920, 1949 (Box 1:, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence to Charles Rufus Harte about the history of the iron industry in the United States, 1934-1935 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings about the early iron industry of the United States, 1937 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Extensive notes written by Herbert Cary Keith, for his book The Early Iron Industry in Connecticut, about the iron industry in the United States, particularly New England, circa 1930s (Box 1:, Folder 5-6)
  - Notes and writings about the early iron industry in Connecticut, particularly blast furnaces, some of which are authored by William Bartlett Murdock, undated, 1935-1937, 1949 (Box 2:, Folder 7)
  - Notes and drafts used in preparation of The Early Iron Industry in Connecticut by Keith and Harte, circa 1932 (Box 2:, Folder 8)
  - Writings and notes about the early iron industry and blast furnaces in Massachusetts, with particular emphasis on the Saugus Iron Works Furnace in Saugus, Massachusetts, undated, 1937, 1948-1949 (Box 2:, Folder 9-10)
  - Writings about the Oxford Furnace of Oxford, New Jersey, 1946 (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Writing about mining in Orange County, New York, 1938 (Box 2:, Folder 12)
  - Notes about the iron industry in Reading, Pennsylvania, undated, 1936 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - Writing about Hopewell Blast Furnace in Pennsylvania, 1930 (Box 2:, Folder 14)